Stanley D. Woodmansee, Jr. Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Stanley D. Woodmansee, Jr. Papers.
1945-1995.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Woodmansee, Stanley D., Jr..
5.25 linear feet.
A graduate of the University of Connecticut (B.A., 1951) and the University of Texas--Austin (M.A.), had a long career in all aspects of music and musicology, including teaching, writing, performing, conducting and directing.
MSS20020034
Biography
Stanley D. Woodmansee, Jr. was born in Waterbury, Connecticut in 1929 and received his education at the University of Connecticut (B.A., 1951) and the University of Texas at Austin (M.A.). His teaching experience includes positions at the University of Texas, Texas State School for the Blind, Cooke County Junior College, Saint Mary's Academy, Saint Edward's University, Keene State College, as well as public schools in Wilton and Lyndeborough, New Hampshire. Woodmansee wrote and produced several original musicals in addition to directing many musical programs and conducting choral organizations at the college and university levels. A gifted musician, Woodmansee participated in numerous organ recitals.
Scope and Content
The collection contains documentation of Mr. Woodmansee's educational and professional career, particularly as it pertains to music. Original musical compositions are represented in the collection, both in draft and finished form. Included in the collection are personal papers, school work, compositions, documentation of several musical productions and compositions.
Organization
The collection is arranged into four series:
Series I: Personal Papers (undated, 1962-1981) contains background and biographical information as well as materials that clearly did not belong in the other three series.
Series II: School work (undated) includes musical compositions, drafts, manuscripts and related materials created by Mr. Woodmansee as part of his educational career.
Series III: Dramatic Productions (undated, 1950-1995) contains materials pertaining to the development, production or direction of three types of dramatic production: Musicals, Plays, and Musical Revues.
Series IV: Classical Compositions (undated, 1945-1970) includes drafts and completed versions of original classical pieces composed by Stanley Woodmansee, both published and unpublished.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection arrangement was determined by Archives & Special Collections staff after determining that there was no perceivable original order.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Let's join the army, a manual of arms and fingers for boys at the piano Dodd XA II.2 no. 129
The Gentle Grafter-Musical Recording 2002-0034.rr1
Ten descriptive sketches: for the pianoforte in the early grades Dodd D1869
Commercially published scores that were probably used in various musical productions have been removed from the collection and returned to the family. These materials fall into six categories:
"Pop" Music
"On the Good Ship Lollipop." Sidney Clare and Richard A. Whiting. Sam Fox Publishing Company. 1934.
"Falling in Love Again (Can't Help It)." Frederick Hollander. Famous Music Company. 1930.
"The Impossible Dream (The Quest)." Joe Darion and Mitch Leigh, arranged by Denes Agay. Sam Fox Publishing Company. 1967.
"We've Only Just Begun." Paul Williams and Roger Nichols.
"I Honestly Love You." Peter Allen and Jeff Barry. Irving Music, Inc., Woolnough Music, Inc., and Broadside Music, Inc. 1974.
"Theme from Ice Castles (Through the Eyes of Love)." Carole Bayer Sayer and Marvin Hamlisch. Good Horizon Music Corporation. 1978.
"To Me." Mack David and Mike Reid, arranged by Jay Althouse. Collins Court Music, Inc. and Lodge Hall Music, Inc. 1984.
"Let It Be Me." G. Bereand. France Music Company. 1960.
Bugles Calls in Tin Pan Alley, 1993
"We Did It Before and We Can Do It Again." Cliff Friend and Charlie Tobias. M. Witmark and Sons. 1941.
"The Last Time I Saw Paris." Oscar Hammerstein II and Jerome Kern. T. B. Harms Company. 1974.
"Don't Fence Me In." Cole Porter. Warner Brothers. 1944
"You'll Never Know." Mack Gordon and Harry Warren. Twentieth Century Music Corporation. 1943.
"I Can't Begin to Tell You." Mack Gordon and James V. Monaco.
"My Ideal." Leo Robin, Richard A. Whiting and Nowell Chase. Famous Music Corporation. 1957.
"Le Vie en Rose." Mark David, Loniguy and Edith Piaf. Warner Brothers. 1950.
"Amor (Amor, Amor, Amor)." Sunny Skylar, Gabriel Ruiz and Ricardo Lopez Mendez. Promotora Hispano Americana de Musica. 1943.
"Bei Mir Bist de Schön." Sholom Secunda, Jacob Jacobs, Sammy Cahn and Saul Chapin. Warner Brothers. 1937.
"I've Got a Gal in Kalamazoo." Mack Gordon and Harry Warden. Warner Brothers Music Corporation. 1942.
"I'll Be Seeing You." Irving Kahall and Sammy Fain. Williamson Music. 1938.
"The Blues in the Night." Harold Arlen. Warner Brothers. 1941.
"I'll be with You in Apple Blossom Time." Neville Fleeson and Albert von Tilzer. Broadway Music Corporation. 1947.
"It's Been a Long, Long Time."Sammy Cahn and Jule Styne.
"(There'll be Blue Birds Over) The White Cliffs of Dover." Nat Burton and Walter Kent.
"God Bless America." Irving Berlin. 1966.
"I'll be Around." Alec Wilder.
"Mairzy Doats." Milton Drake, Al Hoffman and Jerry Livingston.
"Gee, I Wish I was Back in the Army." Irving Berlin. 1954.
"Rum and Coca-Cola." Morey Amsterdam, Al Stillman, Jerry Sullavan and Paul Baro. EMI Feist. 1972.
"It's Love, Love, Lov." Mack David, Joan Whitney and Alex Kramer. Santly-Joyn, Inc. 1943.
"O Beautidul for Spacious Skies." Katharine Lee Bates and Samuel A. Ward.
"Yes, We Have No Bananas." Frank Silver and Irving Cohn.
"I've ot a Lovely Bunch of Cocanuts." Frank Heatherton. Irwin Dash Music Company. 1948.
"As Time Goes By." Herman Hupfeld.
Senior Show, 1992
"Seven Little Girls Sitting in the Back Seat." Bob Hillard and Lee Pockriss.
"Young at Heart." Carolyn Leigh and John Richards. Cherio Corporation. 1954.
"Because of You." Arthur Hammerstein and Dudley Wilkinson. Julian Stearns Arena Music. 1940.
"Hey, Good Lookin'." Hank Williams. Acuff-Rose Music. 1951.
"Paper Doll." Johnny S. Black. Edward B. Marks Music Corporation. 1915.
"All I Have to Do is Dream." Boudleaux Bryan. Acuff-Rose Music. 1958.
"The Great Pretender." Buck Ram. Panther Music Corporation. 1955.
"Return to Me." Carmen Lombardo and Danny Di Minno. Southern Music Publishing Company. 1957.
"(How Much is) That Doggie in the Window?" Bob Merrill.
"Catch a Falling Star." Paul Vance and Lee Pockriss. Marvin Music Company. 1957.
"A White Sport Coat (and a Pink Carnation)." Marty Robins.
The Feast of the Baron's Pleasure
"Santa Baby." Joan Javits, Phil Springer and Tony Springer. Trinity Music. 1953.
The Last Rose of Summer
"Meet Me in Rosetime Rosie." Jean Schwartz and William Jerome. Cohan and Harris Publishing. 1908.
Music for Organ and Trumpet
"Alleluia." J. S. Bach, arranged by Frank Campbell-Watson. H. W. Gray Company. 1964. (First an second B flat Trumpet parts only.)
"Trumpet Fanfare." Jean Joseph Mouret, arranged by S. Drummond Wolff.
"Sonata in D for Two Solo Trumpets, Strings and Contnuo (1680)." Petronio Franceschini. Lowe and Brydone Printers.
"Tocatta pour Trompette et Orgue." Giambattista Martine, ed. Marie-Claire Alain. Editions M. R. Braun. 1970.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Woodmansee, Stanley D.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut
Subjects:
Music teachers--Connecticut--Biography.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Audio visual materials.; Manuscripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Sound recordings.; Scores.
Occupations:
Musician.; Teacher.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Sue Woodmansee Brewer in March 2002.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal papers, undated, 1962-1981
  - Biographical Information and Résumé, undated, 1962-1981 (Box 1:1)
  - Dossier, undated (Box 1:2)
  - Fragments (music), undated (Box 1:3)
  - Kersey Building (Ozona, Texas), undated (Box 1:4)
  - Music for Organ and Trumpet, undated (Box 1:5)
  - Music Composition, undated (Box 1:6)
- Series II: School work, undated
  - Theatre Wing: High School Design Concept, undated (Box 1:7)
  - Aristophanes' The Frogs--Scheme for production, undated (Box 1:8)
  - Mozart's The Magic Flute--Scheme for production, undated (Box 1:9)
  - Four One Act Plays, undated (Box 1:10)
- Series III: Dramatic Productions, undated, 1950-1995
  - Subseries A: Musicals, undated, 1950-1988
    - The Bigger-Better Sunshine-Shadow Circus, ca. 1975
      - [This musical was performed in the mid to late 1970s, although the materials either do not have dates or are dated in the mid 1980s.]
      - Drafts of Score (Box 1:11)
      - Score (Box 1:12)
      - Script and production notes (Box 1:13)
    - The Birds' Christmas Feast--Research materials and first draft, undated (Box 2:14)
    - Blackmen, Molasses & Rum
      - Draft for revision (Box 2:15)
      - Newsprint draft (Box 2:16)
      - Score (Box 2:17)
    - Celestial Journey
      - Working script, 1950 (Box 2:18)
      - Revised script, 1952 (Box 2:19)
      - Working script, 1960 (Box 2:20)
      - Op. 2, 1961 (Box 2:21)
      - Drafts of Score, 1950 (Box 2:22)
      - Score (Op. 2a), undated (Box 3:23)
    - The Courtship of Mr. Frog and Miss Mouse, undated (Box 3:24)
    - The Fisherman's Wife
      - Drafts of script, undated (Box 3:25)
      - Score (drafts and final), undated (Box 3:26)
      - Production notes, 1988 (Box 3:27)
    - The Flag Pole Sitter, undated (Box 3:28)
    - Freedom's Bright Band
      - Production script, 1976 (Box 3:29)
      - Score, undated (Box 3:30)
    - The Gentle Grafter
      - Rough draft, 1957 (Box 3:31)
      - Script, 1957 (Box 3:32)
      - Working script with FRH, 1960 (Box 3:33-34)
      - Production script, 1960 (Box 4:35)
      - Score (drafts), undated (Box 4:36)
      - Score, undated
        - Voice and piano (Box 4:37)
        - Violin I (Box 4:38)
        - Violin II (Box 4:39)
        - Viola (Box 4:40)
        - Violoncella (Box 4:41)
        - Bass (Box 4:42)
        - Reed I (Alto Sax, Flute/Piccolo) (Box 4:43)
        - Reed II (Oboe, Alto Sax, English Horn) (Box 4:44)
        - Reed III (Tenor Sax, B flat Clarinet) (Box 4:45)
        - Reed IV (Baritone Sax, Bassoon) (Box 4:46)
        - French Horn (Box 4:47)
        - Trumpet I (Box 4:48)
        - Trumpet II (Box 4:49)
        - Trombone (Box 4:50)
        - Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:79)
    - A Night at the Movies, undated (Box 4:51)
    - The Kingfish [?], undated (Box 4:52)
    - Mrs. Wiggs of the Cabbage Patch
      - Outline and rough drafts, undated (Box 5:53)
      - First draft, undated (Box 5:54)
      - First typed draft, undated (Box 5:55)
      - Score, 1981-1982 (Box 5:56)
    - My Head and My Heart
      - Drafts, undated (Box 5:57)
      - Drafts (Originals), undated (Box 8:85)
      - Score, undated (Box 5:58)
    - Portsmouth Revisited
      - Drafts (pp. 1-39 missing), undated (Box 5:59)
      - Typed script with music, 1980 (Box 5:60)
  - Subseries B: Plays, undated
    - Warrior's Return, undated (Box 6:61)
    - The Cherry Orchard (Chechov) Set design, undated
  - Subseries C: Musical Revues, undated, 1992-1995
    - The Best Christmas Pageant Ever, 1995 (Box 6:62)
    - The Last Rose of Summer, undated (Box 6:63)
    - Murder at Rutherford House, 1992 (Box 6:64)
    - Bugle Calls in Tin Pan Alley, 1993 (Box 6:65)
    - The Feast of the Baron's Pleasure, undated (Box 6:66)
    - Senior Show, 1992 (Box 6:67)
- Series IV: Classical Compositions, undated, 1945-1970
  - Three Promenades (Op. 3), undated (Box 6:68)
  - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra (Op. 6) Piano score, 1969 (Box 6:69)
  - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra (Op. 6) Orchestra parts, 1969 (Box 6:70)
  - Concerto for Piano and Orchestra (Op. 6) Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:80)
  - Sonatina for Harp (Op. 7), undated (Box 6:71)
  - Summer Quartet for Strings (Op. 8), undated (Box 6:72)
  - Summer Quartet for Strings (Op. 8) Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:81)
  - Ordinary from the Missa Trouperis Diluvei (Op. 9), undated (Box 7:73)
  - Cocierto Romantico en G Minor por Violincelo y Orquestra, undated (Box 7:74)
  - Fantasy to Craig Locke, 1945-1946 (Box 7:75)
  - Vater Unser im Himmelreich, undated (Box 7:76)
  - O Gott Du Frommer Gott (Bach) Orchestration, undated (Box 7:77)
  - O Gott Du Frommer Gott (Bach) Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:82)
  - Wie Schön Leuchtet Der Morgenstern (Bach) Orchestration, undated (Box 7:78)
  - Wie Schön Leuchtet Der Morgenstern (Bach) Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:83)
  - Untitled orchestration Conductor's score, undated (Box 8:84)